David E. Rogers Collection
David E. Rogers Collection
1951-2007
1990-1996
Barondess, Jeremiah A., 1924-
1.2 linear feet; 1 carton
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.
Dr. David E. Rogers was born on March 17, 1926 in New York City. He studied at Ohio State University and Miami University before attending Cornell University Medical College, where he received his medical degree in 1948. He did his residency at the Johns Hopkins Hospital. In 1950 and 1951, he researched infectious diseases with Dr. Walsh McDermott at the New York Hospital. He then served as the Chief Resident in Medicine there from 1951-1952. In 1954 and 1955, Rogers was an Assistant Professor of Medicine at the New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center as well as a visiting investigator at the Rockefeller Institute with Dr. Rene Dubos. He became the Chief of Infectious Diseases at Cornell in 1955. He held the position until 1959, when he was appointed the Chairman of the Department of Medicine at Vanderbilt University and Physician in Chief at the Vanderbilt University Hospital. 1968 brought him back to Johns Hopkins where he was the Dean of the Medical Faculty and Vice President for Medical Affairs. In 1972, he was made the first president of the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, the largest philanthropic organization focused on health. He was the president for 15 years. He moved on from the Foundation to become the first Walsh McDermott University Professor of Medicine at Cornell. Around this time, Dr. Rogers also became very involved in AIDS advocacy, serving on city, state, and national initiatives. He became a senior advisor at the New York Academy of Medicine in 1990. Dr. Rogers died of cancer on December 5, 1994
Rogers received many awards and honors. They include: United States Chamber of Commerce, Ten Outstanding Young Men of the Year Award, 1961; John Hopkins Society of Scholars, 1983; Abraham Flexner Award of the Association of American Medical Colleges, 1986; Distinguished Alumnus of the Vanderbilt School of Medicine, 1990; and the Gustave Leinhard Award of the Institute of Medicine of the National Academy of Sciences, 1993.
Scope and Content
The collection comprises Dr. Jeremiah Barondess' files on his colleague and friend Dr. David E. Rogers. While there are some materials (mostly articles) sent from Rogers to Bardondess, many of the materials were created after Dr. Rogers' death in 1994. These include obituaries, tributes, and correspondence. The collection also includes Rogers' CVs, bibliographies, written works, talks, a transcription of an oral history, and 4 volumes of bound reprints.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Rogers, David E. (David Elliott), 1926-; Oral history.
Container List
  - Curricula Vitae and Bibliographies, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Talks and publications, 1978, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation Oral History Project: Reminisces of Dr. David E. Rogers, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - An African AIDS Diary, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Gustav O. Lienhard Award, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Visiting Nurse Service Award, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and NYAM Memorial, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - NYAM Memorial Service Programs and Pamphlets, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center Lunch and Tribute, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reflections, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Bound reprints, 1951-1994 (Box 1)
Provenance
Gift of Dr. Jeremiah Barondess, June 2012.